Guide to the Rene Boylesve research materials, 1950-1967 MS 589
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rene Boylesve research materials
1950-1967
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Bourgeois, Andre
MS 589
1 Linear Feet 2 boxes
The material in this collection consists of papers from the files of Andre M.G. Bourgeois, Professor of Romance Languages, at Rice University, concerning the life of Rene Boylseve, with particular reference to poems, written by him to Betty Halperine During the First World War. Rene Boylesve was the pseudonym of Rene-marie-auguste Tardiveau, a French novelist noted for his social histories set in the Touraine region of west-central France. He was elected to the French Academy in 1918. (2 boxes)
Biographical / Historical
Rene Boylesve was the pseudonym of Rene-marie-auguste Tardiveau, a French novelist noted for his social histories set in the Touraine region of west-central France. He was elected to the French Academy in 1918.
Scope and Contents
The material in this collection consists of papers from the files of Andre M.G. Bourgeois, Professor of Romance Languages, at Rice University, concerning the life of Rene Boylseve, with particular reference to poems, written by him to Betty Halperine during the World War I. Correspondents include Betty Halperine (Rene Boylesve's mistress 1914-1926), Jeanne Armand Calliat, and Marie Mors-Boylesve (sister of Rene Boylseve).
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from June M. Bourgeois, September 2011.
Index Terms
Subjects
Literature; French poetry; Poetry
Document Types
notes; corrrespondence; black-and-white photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Boylesve, René
- Series I: Correspondence, 1950-1967, 158342
  - Correspondence to Andre Bourgeois, 1953-1955, 158376 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Betty Halperine to Andre Bourgeois, 1952-1966, 158377 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jeanne Armand Calliat to Andre Bourgeois, 1953, 158378 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Marie Mors-Bloylesve to Andre Bourgeois, 1950-1962, 158379 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence regarding Bouregois' publication of Borlesve poems, 1967, 158382 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Research Notes by Bourgeois on Boylesve, 158370
  - Poems to Betty Halperine (typewritten and handwritten copies), 158384 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boylesve family history notes, 158385 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bourgeois book notes, 158386 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Auguste Chevigne "Le jardin secret" notes, 158387 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Publications, 158392 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence regarding Tardiveau, 1955, 158393 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tardiveau family chronology notes, 158394 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tardiveau title papers (typescript copy), 158395 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: Photographs, 158372
  - Unidentified image of man at desk, possibly Boylesve, 158396 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sculpture of Boylesve in a garden, 1951, 158397 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Portrait identified as Numa Blanc, Monte Carlo, G. Detaille, 158398 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Writing (by Boylesve), 180441
  - Le Parfum des Iles Borromees, 180442 (Box 2)
  - La Lecon d'Amour dans un Parc, 180443 (Box 2)
  - La Becquee, 180444 (Box 2)
  - Almanach des Verlages 1904-1914, R. Piper & Co., Munchen, 180445 (Box 2)
  - Sainte Marie des Fleurs, 180446 (Box 2)
  - Madeleine Jeune Femme, 180447 (Box 2)
  - Le Medecin des Dames de Neans, 180448 (Box 2)
  - Les Nouvelles Lecons d'Amour dans un Parc, 180449 (Box 2)
  - Le Parfum des Iles Borromees cinquieme edition 1899, 180450 (Box 2)
  - Feuilles Tombees (Ecrits intimes), 180451 (Box 2)
  - Le Confort Moderne, 180452 (Box 2)
  - Les Amis des Rene Boylesve, Bulletin No. 1, 1953; Bulletin no. 2, 1955, 180453 (Box 2)